<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter>
  <article lang="en">
    <articleinfo>
      <title>Debugging_the_Code</title>
    </articleinfo><section>
      <sectioninfo>
        <title>Debugging_the_Code</title>
      </sectioninfo><para>By Greg DeKoenigsberg </para>
      <section>
        <sectioninfo>
          <title>Introduction </title>
        </sectioninfo><para>It would be foolhardy to try to teach the practice of software quality assurance in one chapter.  It's a vast field, and there are plenty of places to learn about the difference between <emphasis>white-box</emphasis> and <emphasis>black-box</emphasis> testing, or how to write the best possible <emphasis>regression tests</emphasis>. Those are all worthy fields of study, and you should pursue them -- but they are far beyond the scope of this chapter.</para><para>Besides, the simple fact is that for most software projects, bugs are not so uncommon that you need to go looking for them.  They find you.  Sometimes in bunches. </para>
        <para>What makes FOSS interesting, and different, is that <emphasis>you can actually do something about the bugs</emphasis>.</para><para>Eric S. Raymond once said that "with enough eyes, all bugs are shallow."  This aphorism has become one of the central tenets of FOSS -- but it's only half of the story.  The real strength of FOSS lies in the ability of motivated individuals to record, research, and resolve those bugs.  Seeing bugs is one thing; reporting them is another; fixing them is something else.   </para>
        <para>In this chapter, you learn some of the practical techniques that FOSS developers use to find, report, investigate, and fix bugs -- and you begin to contribute, in earnest, to real FOSS projects.  You will join the global collaborative effort to solve real problems, for real users, in real software. </para>
      </section><section>
        <sectioninfo>
          <title>Bug Trackers </title>
        </sectioninfo><para>Any project worth your time has a bug tracker of some kind.  Almost every provider of FOSS project infrastructure provides access to bug tracking software, for free.  If the project doesn't have a bug tracker, it's a pretty good indication that they're Doing It Wrong, and you should stay away.  Far, far away. </para>
        <section>
          <sectioninfo>
            <title>What is a Bug Tracker, Exactly? </title>
          </sectioninfo><para>A bug tracker for a FOSS project is a web application that allows users to enter bug reports about a software project.  These bug reports then go into a database, where they can be tracked and managed as the developers work to fix them.  </para>
          <para>There are many different bug trackers available for use by FOSS projects.  Most of them collect very similar information: </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Summary</emphasis>, a short description of the bug.  For example: "Toaster always burns toast".  This short phrase is usually what the developer sees in his or her list of bugs.</para>
            </listitem><listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Description</emphasis>, a more detailed description of the bug, ideally with lots of clues.  This is where the reporter explains what he or she was doing, what was expected to happen, and what happened instead.  For example, "I have a BreadNuke toaster model XZ-38, and it never works.  I expect it to brown my toast nicely; but it always burns my toast instead.  I've tried setting the knob from 0 to 9, and the toast always comes out completely black!"</para>
            </listitem><listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Comments</emphasis>, which allow other users or developers to add information to the bug.  For example, a user might say "it burns my toast too!"  Or, a developer might respond "the docs for the XZ-38 specify that it's for creating Blackened Toast".  For a complex bug, there can be literally hundreds of comments attached to the bug report.</para>
            </listitem><listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Reporter</emphasis> is the email address or account name of the user who reported the bug.</para>
            </listitem><listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Owner</emphasis> is the email address or account name of the developer assigned to fix the bug.</para>
            </listitem><listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Version</emphasis>.  When there are multiple versions of the software, it's obviously important to know which version the bug appears in.</para>
            </listitem><listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Severity</emphasis> and <emphasis>Priority</emphasis>.  Severity, usually set initially by the user, indicates the impact that a bug has.  Priority, usually set initially by the developer, indicates which bugs receive attention first.  In practice, these two can be confusing, and sometimes a project chooses to pay attention to only one of them.</para>
            </listitem><listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Status</emphasis>, which describes the state a bug is in.  Bugs start with a <emphasis>new</emphasis> status, and then they become <emphasis>assigned</emphasis> when a developer is tasked to work on them.  The ultimate goal is to move a bug's status to <emphasis>closed</emphasis>.</para>
            </listitem><listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis>Resolution</emphasis>, which is particular to closed bugs.  <emphasis>Fixed</emphasis> means just that: the bug was fixed.  <emphasis>Nextrelease</emphasis> indicates that a bug has been fixed, but won't be available to users until the next release of the software.  Users often file bugs that aren't actually bugs, but are the result of user error; such bugs are closed as <emphasis>invalid</emphasis> or <emphasis>notabug</emphasis>.  Lots of bugs are duplicates of one another, so bugs are often closed as <emphasis>duplicate</emphasis> with a reference to a single authoritative bug report.  Occasionally, a bug is just not worth the work required to close it; these bugs are closed <emphasis>wontfix</emphasis>. </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist><para>Because all of this data is collected in a structured way, it becomes much easier to sort through the bugs for meaningful data -- which becomes essential as the project grows, and the bugs multiply. </para>
        </section>
      </section><section>
        <sectioninfo>
          <title>Sorting Through the Bugs </title>
        </sectioninfo><para>Much of a software developer's life is spent fixing bugs, and there are almost always more bugs than there is time to fix those bugs -- which means that having a good way of deciding which bugs are important, at any given time, is crucial.   </para>
        <para>All bug trackers have functionality for searching bugs by detailed criteria.  Some common searches that developers might run, for instance: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para> "What's new and broken today?"  Find every bug with a status of <emphasis>new</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem><listitem>
            <para> "What should I work on first today?"  Find every high priority bug assigned to the developer. </para>
          </listitem><listitem>
            <para> "What bugs did we close that should go in the notes for our upcoming release?"  Find all of the bugs with the latest version, that have a status of <emphasis>closed</emphasis> and a resolution of <emphasis>fixed</emphasis> or <emphasis>nextrelease</emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><para>And so on.   </para>
      </section><section>
        <sectioninfo>
          <title>Exercise: Find the Oldest Bug </title>
        </sectioninfo><para>Find the oldest bug that's still open in your chosen project.  Write a blog entry describing the problem, with a theory about why the bug hasn't been resolved yet.  (Bonus points if you can actually resolve the bug.) </para>
      </section><section>
        <sectioninfo>
          <title>Exercise: Create Your Bug Tracker Account </title>
        </sectioninfo><para>Figure out how to create a new account on the bug tracker of your chosen project.  You'll need that account very soon. </para>
      </section><section>
        <sectioninfo>
          <title>The Anatomy of a Good Bug Report </title>
        </sectioninfo><para>Take a closer look at the bugs in your project's bug tracker.  In particular, spend some time looking through bugs in the <emphasis>new</emphasis> state.</para><para>It's certain that some of these bug reports are not be very useful.  </para>
        <para>For software to improve over time, good bug reports are absolutely essential.  Users who file bugs, while almost always well-meaning, frequently don't know how to write good bug reports -- which is a problem, but also an opportunity for others to make positive contributions.  Turning a bad bug report into a good bug report doesn't require special developer knowledge; it just requires patience, persistence, a solid understanding of how the software works, and an understanding of what good bug reports look like. </para>
        <para>So what does a good bug report look like?  Look at some of the characteristics of good bug reports. </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Good bugs have descriptive summaries.</emphasis>
        </para><programlisting>  Bad: 		Audio player hangs  Good: 	Audio Player stutters when playing some kinds of audio files  Best:		Audio Player stutters when playing .mp3/.wav files &gt; 35Mb, patch attached</programlisting>
        <para>Software developers, like most people, are busy and lazy in roughly equal parts.  When a developer has decided to spend a day "fixing bugs," that developer likely starts by scanning the bug list.  If she see a bug summary that says "your program is broken," it's unlikely to provoke a favorable response.  Summaries matter.  The goal is to pack as much information into a single line of text.  The more information the developer sees in a bug summary, the more likely he is to dig into that bug. </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Good bugs refer to the version of the software.</emphasis>
        </para><programlisting>  Bad:		Zombie-buster version... two-something?  Good:		Zombie-buster-1.2.4  Best:		Zombie-buster-1.2.4 and confirmed in HEAD, svn checkout 1361</programlisting>
        <para>Most of the time, the bug tracker you use has a predefined field for version.  That field is a good start, but sometimes the entries can be outdated, and even if there's an entry for <emphasis>HEAD</emphasis> (i.e. the very latest code in the SCM), it's still important to provide the most detailed version information that you can possibly provide.  What you absolutely must NOT do: ignore this field.  If you can't figure out what version of the software you're running, then you probably shouldn't even file a bug.</para><para>
          <emphasis>Good bugs provide relevant system information.</emphasis>
        </para><programlisting>  Bad: 		I'm running Linux, if that matters.  Good:		I'm running Gnome 2.28 on Fedora 12.    Best:		Gnome 2.28, Fedora 12, nVidia Corporation G70 GeForce 7800 GTX (rev a1)</programlisting>
        <para>It's easy to provide way too much of this kind of information, but that's a forgivable sin: it's certainly better than providing none at all, which is too frequently the case.  Over time, you develop a feel for which information to provide -- and if you become a trusted contributor to a project, developers feel more comfortable asking for precisely the information they need.  Until developers say otherwise, it's usually best to err on the side of providing too much info.  (Within reason.  Dumping the entire contents of gigantic log files into a bug report is clearly bad form, but a relevant log file may be attached to a bug report.) </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Good bugs only report a single issue.</emphasis>
        </para><programlisting>  Bad:		When I load the latest Foomail client, it crashes.  Also, I'm getting screen lockups in Barchat.  I think they're related.  Good:		Bug 1: Foomail client crashes.  Bug 2: Lockups in Barchat.  Best:		Bug 1: Foomail client crashes.  I think it may be related to lockups in Barchat (and here's some evidence).  Bug 2: Lockups in Barchat.  I think it might be related to Foomail client crashes (and here's some evidence).</programlisting>
        <para>It's tempting sometimes to see multiple issues, convince yourself that they are related, and then file a single bug on the whole thing.   </para>
        <para>Don't do that.  You may very well be right that the issues are related -- but you may also be wrong, and in either case, two different issues deserve two different bug reports.  In our example above, it may be that the issues with <emphasis>Foomail</emphasis> and <emphasis>Barchat</emphasis> are actually related to a problem with <emphasis>Bazlib</emphasis>, which is a shared component of <emphasis>Foomail</emphasis> and <emphasis>Barchat</emphasis>.  Each bug must be fixed and tested in its own context, and that won't work if they're all stuffed in the same bug report.</para><para>
          <emphasis>Good bugs are followed by people who care about a solution.</emphasis>
        </para><programlisting>  Bad:		What, you said file a bug, I filed a bug.  I don't care if you fix it.  How do I turn off these email notifications?  Good:		Hey, I checked the latest version like you asked, and it still isn't fixed.  Do you need more info?  Best:		I kept poking at this bug, and this log entry makes me think it's somewhere in libfoo.  I'll keep digging.</programlisting>
        <para>Never underestimate the power of attention.  The more you care about a particular bug, the more likely it is that the developer will care about it.  The more work you do to chase it down, the more obligated the developer feels to spend some time on it also, and the more appreciative he or she is.  If you file a bug that no one cares enough to follow up on, not even you, then why should the developer care enough to fix it?  Especially if there are other bugs that people do care about? </para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Good bugs are reproducible with the fewest possible steps.</emphasis>
        </para><programlisting>  Bad:		start it and click around for a while and then it crashes  Good:		Start the application.  Click the mouse button and type on the keyboard.  Within 45 seconds or less, the application will always crash.  Best:		Start the application.  Click the mouse five times, and the application crashes with the following error message in "/var/log/foo.err"...</programlisting>
        <para>Anybody can break software.  People break software all the time.  But it takes a bit of practice and skill to break things predictably, over and over -- and if there's no one exercising this skill on a project's behalf, it's much more difficult to improve that project over time.  That's why software companies hire testers (although they almost never hire as many as they should.) </para>
        <para>Reproducing bugs is one of the best ways to learn how software actually works.  A tester who has explored a bug thoroughly, and who can confidently say "this bug only happens when these three conditions are met," is much more likely to be able to take the next step: namely, to dig in and find the code that actually creates those three conditions.  </para>
        <para>Sometimes it's not possible to reproduce a bug 100% of the time.  Intermittent bugs are extremely frustrating for both testers and developers; they are frequently the result of complex software interactions, and reproducing the bug is actually the hardest part of fixing it.  In such cases, testers should do their best to provide as much information as possible, and be ready to answer a developer's questions. </para>
        <section>
          <sectioninfo>
            <title>Exercise: Reproduce a Bug </title>
          </sectioninfo><para>Go through your project's bug tracker and find a bug that you think you might be able to reproduce -- and then try to reproduce it in the latest build.  Take careful notes.  Report your experiences as a comment to the bug.  If you can reproduce the bug, great!  Give as much information as you can.  If you can't reproduce the bug, great!  Give as much information as you can, and ask the original reporter if there are other steps you might be able to take to reproduce the bug. </para>
        </section>
      </section><section>
        <sectioninfo>
          <title>Bug Triage </title>
        </sectioninfo><para>Some projects receive a handful of bug reports.  Some projects receive tens of thousands of bug reports.   </para>
        <para>All projects have overworked developers.  In software projects, there are almost always more bugs than time to fix them. </para>
        <para>The term <emphasis>triage</emphasis> is borrowed from the medical profession, in which patients are stabilized and prioritized based on the severity of their condition.  In the same way that patients are prioritized, bugs can be prioritized.  Bug triage saves critical time for developers, and moves the project forward.  It's one of the most useful and instructive activities in which a newbie can engage.</para><para>Some projects have entire teams devoted to bug triage.  A few examples: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <ulink url="http://live.gnome.org/Bugsquad/TriageGuide"> The GNOME Bug Squad</ulink>
            </para>
          </listitem><listitem>
            <para>
              <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/BugZappers"> The Fedora BugZappers team</ulink>
            </para>
          </listitem><listitem>
            <para>
              <ulink url="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/Bugs/HowToTriage"> Ubuntu Bug triage</ulink>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><para>There are many more examples of bug triage teams -- but even those projects that don't have a dedicated team can still benefit greatly from bug triage.   </para>
        <para>Triaging a bug generally means: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Letting the user know that someone has looked at it.</emphasis>  This simple courtesy is frequently overlooked.  Bug trackers send emails to the original reporter whenever the state of a bug changes in any way -- and when a user files a bug and never hears any response at all, it's discouraging and makes it less likely that the user will bother to file another bug.  A response such as, "thanks for reporting, I'll try to reproduce today" can be very helpful.</para>
          </listitem><listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Looking for other similar bugs.</emphasis>  A large percentage of bugs filed against FOSS projects are duplicates; users frequently report bugs without searching to see if similar bugs have already been filed.  Finding duplicates becomes easier with a bit of practice; the more familiar you are with a program, and the more you communicate with its developers, and the more bugs you see coming through the bug tracker, the more likely it is that you know when a bug is a duplicate.  Still, even an inexperienced triager can spot obvious duplicates.</para>
          </listitem><listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Guaranteeing proper severity and/or priority.</emphasis>  Users tend to think that their bugs are the most important issues in the world.  Sometimes, they're right.  Often, they're not.  Part of the triager's job is to make a good faith estimate of a bug's severity and priority. It's an imperfect process, so triagers are also be wrong sometimes -- but experienced bug triagers are much less wrong.</para>
          </listitem><listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Ensuring that the bug is sensible and helpful to developers.</emphasis>  A poorly written bug report should never even make its way into the developer's queue.  If a bug report is filed with absolutely no information, it's the triager's job to get that information -- with a politely worded comment in the bug, something like this: "Thanks for filing the bug, but there isn't much information here.  Could you help by telling us what version of Barchat you're running, and if possible, attach the last 100 lines of ~/.barchatlog?"</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis>Ensuring that the bug is filed against the correct component, with the correct version.</emphasis>  Sometimes, bugs are simply filed with the wrong information in some of the fields and it is obviously wrong.  When a bug report about <programlisting format="linespecific">foomail</programlisting> accidentally gets filed against <programlisting format="linespecific">foomatic</programlisting>, reassiging that bug to the right component is simple -- but vital.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist><para>
          <emphasis>Take note!  If you can do these things well, you are building job references with real developers, right now.</emphasis>  If you are doing it right at this point, you may be setting yourself up for a job down the line.</para><section>
          <sectioninfo>
            <title>Exercise: Bug Triage </title>
          </sectioninfo><para>Find five bug reports in the <emphasis>new</emphasis> state, and attempt to triage them according to the rules above.  Your goal is to do as much as you possibly can, in a short period of time, to make those bug reports as useful as possible to the developer to whom they are assigned.  (Note: be sure to follow any triage rules that your project may have defined.  If there are no set triage rules, be sure to announce your intentions on the project's mailing list, so that developers can provide you some guidelines if they choose.)</para>
        </section>
      </section><section>
        <sectioninfo>
          <title>Supplemental Reading </title>
        </sectioninfo><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para> The Fedora project has good guidelines for bug reporters: <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Bugs_and_feature_requests"> Bugs and feature requests</ulink> and <ulink url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/How_to_file_a_bug_report"> How to file a bug report</ulink>.  A bit specific to Fedora in places, but very instructive. </para>
          </listitem><listitem>
            <para> The Mozilla project also has a set of <ulink url="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/page.cgi?id=bug-writing.html"> bug reporting guidelines</ulink>, and a great <ulink url="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/page.cgi?id=etiquette.html"> etiquette guide</ulink> as well.  Specific to Mozilla, but instructive. </para>
          </listitem><listitem>
            <para> Simon Tatham's <ulink url="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/bugs.html"> How to Report Bugs Effectively</ulink> is a truly outstanding work.  Strongly recommended. </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section><section>
        <sectioninfo>
          <title>Supplemental Exercises </title>
        </sectioninfo><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para> Find the developer to whom the most bugs are assigned.  Find all bugs in the <emphasis>new</emphasis> state that have not been reproduced, and try to reproduce them.</para>
          </listitem><listitem>
            <para> Figure out how to get yourself put on the default <emphasis>Cc:</emphasis> of a particular bug or component, so that you see new bug reports in your email.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </article>
</chapter>
